<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Git on vaneyckt.io</title>
    <link>https://vaneyckt.io/topics/git/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Git on vaneyckt.io</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Tom Van Eyck</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2014 19:32:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vaneyckt.io/topics/git/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding and deleting old tags in a Github repository</title>
      <link>https://vaneyckt.io/posts/finding_and_deleting_old_tags_in_a_github_repo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2014 19:32:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vaneyckt.io/posts/finding_and_deleting_old_tags_in_a_github_repo/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s very easy for a Github repository to accumulate lots of tags over time. This onslaught of tags tends to be tolerated until it starts impacting git performance. It is at this point, when you have well in excess of tens of thousands of tags, that a call to action tends to be made. In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll look at two approaches to rid yourself of these old tags.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some lesser known Github API functionality</title>
      <link>https://vaneyckt.io/posts/some_lesser_known_github_api_functionality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2014 18:05:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vaneyckt.io/posts/some_lesser_known_github_api_functionality/</guid>
      <description>One of our automation tools occasionally needs to interact with our Github repositories. Unfortunately, the current implementation of this tool leaves something to be desired as it requires cloning these repositories to local disk. Changes against these local repositories are then made on local branches, after which these branches get pushed to Github.
However, in order to save on disk space this tool will only ever create a single local copy of each repository.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bug hunting with git bisect</title>
      <link>https://vaneyckt.io/posts/bug_hunting_with_git_bisect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 20:02:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vaneyckt.io/posts/bug_hunting_with_git_bisect/</guid>
      <description>Today I was looking into what I thought was going to be a simple bug. The problem seemed straightforward enough, so I did a quick grep of the codebase, found three pieces of code that looked like likely culprits, made some modifications, triggered the bug, and found that absolutely nothing had changed. Half an hour and a lot of additional digging later I was stumped. I had no idea what was going on.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>